in this video I'm going to compare the
key action sound quality features and
functionality of two of the most
affordable keyboards with 88 weighted
Hammer action keys from two established
and extremely popular Japanese brands
Yamaha and Casio I will play the sounds
from these two keyboards side by side so
you have a direct comparison as to which
sound you prefer these two models the
Yamaha p45 and the Casio CDP s 160 are
the cheapest new digital pianos you can
buy as at the time of this video with
just a mere 20 difference between these
two keyboards it is clear the two
Japanese Giants are trying to capture
the price sensitive markets while Casio
has an even cheaper CDP S110 it isn't
available in many markets and I've
excluded it from this comparison I have
links to the best prices for these two
digital camera channels as well as my
recommended keyboards and music learning
apps in the description like a
traditional acoustic piano both the p45
and the CDP s160 have 88 full size keys
and a graded Hammer action but the
response of these two keys cannot be
more different the keys on the p45 have
a firmer weight to it which I prefer
versus the cdps 160 which has a lighter
feel the keys on the p45 are also
quieter while the action on the cdps 160
is less dampened I love the matte and
textured black and white keys on the
cdps 160 which simulates natural Ebony
and Ivory Only The Black Keys on the p45
have a matte finish while the white keys
are glossy my fingers stay planted
better on the CDP s160 versus the glossy
p45 keys however I can extract a more
controlled dynamic range from yamaha's
ghs Key action on the p45 even though
both these keyboards come with four
velocity of Curves if you spend a little
extra there is another key action which
is better and I'll link to it in the
description the capability of the sound
engine on these keyboards are very
similar both keyboards come with 64 note
polyphony and 10 voices but the voice
selection on these keyboards are quite
different the Casio comes with three
grand piano voices while the Yamaha
comes with just two here's how they
sound
[Music]
foreign
thank you
[Music]
[Applause]
foreign
[Music]
comes with a selection of three electric
piano voices while the p45 has just two
let me know which you prefer in the
comments
[Music]
foreign
decided that we should get two pipe
organs and two harpsichords on the p45
while Casio gives us just one pipe organ
and one harpsichord on the CDP s160.
[Music]
I personally prefer two string patches
one with a faster attack for melodic
lines and another with a slower attack
for large ballads but both keyboards
come with just one string patch each
[Music]
foreign
on the Yamaha is a vibraphone and on the
Casio we get a jazz organ
[Music]
if you find 10 voices to be inadequate I
have links to piano keyboards with up to
600 onward sounds in the description
while both these keyboards allow you to
layer two voices at the same time Yamaha
allows us to balance the volume of the
two voice layers which you cannot do on
the Casio on both these pianos there is
no option to split different sounds
across the keyboard which in never
similarly priced digital piano can and
I'll leave a link to it in the
description both Brands include a basic
sustain pedal in the box but Advanced
players will prefer Casio support for an
optional triple pedal unit giving you
soft sustenuto and damper controls
Yamaha believes buyers of this keyboard
are most likely to be beginners and
therefore the p45 does not support soft
and sustain uto subscribe and smash that
like button if you are getting value
from this video so far it really helps
my Channel with YouTube's algorithm if
you want to tweak The Sounds the Casio
Keyboard gives you four rebook and four
chorus effects while the Yamaha has just
four Reverb effects and no chorus is
available these are meant to be practice
pianos and you can find a metronome
a transpose function and the ability to
tune the keyboard to match other
musicians Casio however has gone one
step further by giving us 16 additional
scale systems Baroque Middle Eastern
Oriental and World music do not use the
typical equal temperament tuning and the
cdps 160 has you covered A major
advantage of digital pianos is the
ability to use headphones for quiet
practice both these keyboards come with
a single headphone jack but the Casio
favors a three and a half millimeter
mini jack while the Yamaha uses a more
robust quarter inch connector my
favorite pair of headphones is in the
description even though the CDP s 160 is
a more compact unit it manages to pack
in a more powerful amplification system
a pair of 8 watts amplifiers gives you a
total output of 6 16 watts versus the 12
watts output on the Yamaha you have the
option to stream music from your mobile
device to the onboard speakers using an
auxiliary audio cable but the Casio uses
a three and a half millimeter Jack
whereas Yamaha has a more robust quarter
inch Jack which I personally prefer
wireless audio streaming via Bluetooth
is unfortunately not available on both
these two models
another model I recommend with Bluetooth
wireless streaming is in the description
the Casio keyboard has a single song
Single track recorder which is really
useful for capturing your performance
there is no way to record your playing
on the Yamaha p45 however both these
keyboards come with a USB midi
connection allowing you to record to
Advanced music production software and
connect to music learning apps for
interactive lessons on your iPad or
laptop my favorite music learning apps
are in the description the cdps 160 is
the king of portability at 23 pounds not
only is it two pounds lighter than the
Yamaha Keyboard it is also 2 inch
shallower and three inch shorter making
it significantly easier to handle if you
intend to bring it out while both these
digital pianos come with an AC adapter
for operating of an electrical outlet
the Casio wins Big on its ability to use
regular double a batteries for power
at campsites while basking or on a road
trip an electrical outlet may not always
be within reach and this is where the
Casio CDP s 160 shines while you can
simply switch on and play the various
voices on these keyboards the Casio is
better when it comes to user
friendliness every available parameter
is printed on the chassis making it easy
to make changes without referring to the
user manual on the Yamaha apart from the
regular voice selection you will not be
able to make changes such as tuning
transposing and balancing the layer
volumes without referencing the user
manual don't forget to check out my
recommended digital pianos keyboards and
music learning apps in the description
smash that like button if you found my
review helpful my name is Jeremy C and
here's another video you should watch